<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Chapter>
    <Title> Abstract Interfaces </Title>
    <Author>
        <Name> A. Pasetti </Name>
        <Affiliation>
            <a HREF="http://www.pnp-software.com">P&amp;P Software</a>
        </Affiliation>
        <EMail> pasetti@pnp-software.com </EMail>
    </Author>
    <LastModified> 2003-12-08 </LastModified>
    <Introduction>
        <p> Abstract interfaces are one of the building blocks that are provided by the OBS
            Framework. Abstract interfaces are introduced to support the instantiation of the <a
                href="indexDesignPatterns.html" target="_parent">framework design patterns</a>. An
            abstract interface defines a set of services that must be provided by the framework but
            it leaves their implementation open. The framework can provide default implementations
            (as <a href="indexConcreteComponents.html" target="_parent">concrete components</a>) or
            it can leave the implementation entirely open and to be specified at application level.</p>
        <p>In general, the mapping of the abstract interface concept to a concrete architectural
            construct in a framework depends on the facilities provided by the language selected for
            the implementation of the framework. In the case of the OBS Framework, the
            implementation language is C++. An abstract interface in C++ is normally implemented as
            a class that only declares pure virtual methods. This, however, is regarded as too
            restrictive. A more flexible approach is to use a class with virtual methods since this
            allows for the possibility of providing a default implementation of some of the
            interface services. The fact that the services are implemented through virtual methods
            means that they can be overridden with application-specific implementations.
            </p><p>
            There is a second reason for the choice to implement the framework abstract interfaces
            as C++ abstract classes. The use of C++ pure virtual classes to represent abstract interfaces
            would require the use of multiple inheritance but this is excluded in the case of the OBS
            Framework because of the desire to remain within the EC++ subset of the language (see
            the discussion of the <a href="indexQualificationApproach.html#CppCodeQuality">framework code quality</a>).
            </p>
    </Introduction>
</Chapter>
