<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Chapter>
    <Title> Installation Issues </Title>
    <Author>
        <Name> A. Pasetti </Name>
        <Affiliation>
            <a HREF="http://www.pnp-software.com">P&amp;P Software</a>
        </Affiliation>
        <EMail> pasetti@pnp-software.com </EMail>
    </Author>
    <LastModified> 2004-04-29 </LastModified>
    <Introduction>
        <p>The OBS Framework is delivered as one single web site that contains all the framework
            documentation and gives access to all its code including source code, meta-component
            code, and command files. The OBS Framework should normally be expanded in a dedicated
            directory called <code>ObsFramework</code>. This page discusses some issues related to
            the installation and usage of the OBS Framework web site. 
            </p>
    </Introduction>
    <Section Title="Web Site Structure">
        <p>The HTML pages that make up the OBS Framework web site are automatically generated by XSL
            programs that process a set of XML documents. The appearance of the web site can be
            customized by modifying the XSL programs. Customization of these programs would also
            allow generation of the OBS Framework documentation in a format other than HTML (e.g.
            PDF). The xsl programs that generate the web site can be found in the project directory
            <code>doc/xsl</code>.
        </p>   
        <p>All the figures used by the web site are stored in the project directory <code>figures</code>.
            The hyperlinks to the figures are automatically generated by the XSL transformations.</p>
            

        <p> The generation of the OBS Framework web site can be done automatically by calling the default target
            in the Ant command file <a href="../scripts/build.xml">
                <code>build.xml</code>
            </a>. The interpretation of the XML files is done by the <a
                href="http://saxon.sourceforge.net/">Saxon XSLT processor</a>.</p>


    </Section>
    <Section Title="Command Files">
        <p>A number of command files are provided in the <code>/scripts</code> directory of the OBS
            Framework. Command files are implemented as Apache Ant build files. The Ant command
            processor is not included in the OBS Framework delivery but can be downloaded at no cost
            from the <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant web site</a>. The meta-components
            require version 1.1 of the XSLT processor. During the development of the OBS Framework,
            the Saxon XSLT processor was used. This processor may not be included in the default
            Apache Ant delivery. The corresponding <code>saxon.jar</code> file can be downloaded from
            the <a href="http://saxon.sourceforge.net/">Saxon web site</a> and must then be placed
            in the <code>lib</code> directory of the Ant command processor.</p>
        <p> The master command file is <code>build.xml</code>. Its default target processes the <a
                href="indexModellingApproach.html">framework feature models</a>, generates the HTML pages
            that make up the web site, generates the <a href="doxygen/html/index.html">doxygen
                documentation of the source code</a>, and runs all the <a
                href="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html">generator meta-components</a> associated to the framework.</p>
        <p>The command directory also contains the makefile that is used to build the <a
                href="indexQualificationApproach.html#TestSuite">regression test</a> of the OBS Framework
            under a Linux environment.</p>
        <p>The code documentation is automatically generated using 
        the (open and free software) facility <a href="http://www.stack.nl/~dimitri/doxygen/">doxygen</a>.
        The Ant command file requires doxygen to be available on the host platform. Depending on where
        the doxygen executable is located, the "doxygen"property in the Ant build file may have to
        be modified.
		</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="Project Files">
        <p>For the convenience of some users, the OBS Framework includes four project subdirectories
            (in directory <code>projects</code>). Two projects are <a
            href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/">oxygen</a> projects that cover the definition of the
            framework models and of the web site, respectively. The third and fourth project
            subdirectories contain Microsoft Visual Studio (version 7.1) projects of which the first
            cover the <a href="indexQualificationApproach.html#TestSuite">regression test</a> whereas the
            second one covers the sample application test that is used in the <a
                href="indexImplementationIssues.html#MemoryOccupation">memory occupation tests</a>. Note
            that the VS environment hardcodes the full path of the files it manipulates. The VS
            projects files included in the OBS Framework delivery assume that the framework web site
            is placed in directory: <code>D:/Projects/ObsFramework</code>.</p>
    </Section>
</Chapter>
