<Chapter>
    <Title> PUS Compatibility </Title>
    <Author>
        <Name> A. Pasetti </Name>
        <Affiliation>
            <a HREF="http://www.pnp-software.com">P&amp;P Software</a>
        </Affiliation>
        <EMail> pasetti@pnp-software.com </EMail>
    </Author>
    <LastModified> 2003-12-05 </LastModified>
    <Introduction>
        <p>The OBS Framework is designed for general use but is in particular compatible with the
            Packet Utilization Standard (PUS) defined in ESA's ECSS-E-70-41. This page discusses the
            extent of this compatibility and in particular the extent to which the services defined
            by the PUS are directly supported by the OBS Framework.</p>
    </Introduction>
    <Section Title="Compatibility Model">
        <p>In PUS terms, the OBS Framework can be used to instantiate an <i>application process</i>.
            The architecture that is implied by the OBS Framework is shown in the figure:
            <Figure>PUSCompatibility_1</Figure> The shaded items are provided by the OBS Framework.
            The packet router must instead be provided externally. From the point of view of the
            application process the packet router has two functions. It must make available the PUS
            telecommand packets that have the application process as their destination and it must
            receive the PUS telemetry packets that the application process generates. The interfaces
            between the packet router and the application process are
            the<cls>TelecommandLoader</cls> and the <cls>TelemetryStream</cls> classes. Note that
            these are abstract classes. Applications will have to instantiate them to take account
            of the exact interface of the packet router. The telecommand loader interprets the PUS
            packet and uses its content to build a component of type<cls>Telecommand</cls> that
            encapsulates the telecommand. This is then executed by
            the<cls>CC_TelecommandManager</cls> component. In a symmetric process, telemetry packets
            are represented inside the application process by components of
            type<cls>TelemetryPacket</cls>. The content of the telemetry items is written to the
            telemetry stream by the<cls>CC_TelemetryManager</cls> component. The task of the
            telemetry stream is to transfer the telemetry data to the packet router.</p>
        <p>In order to preserve generality and to be useful in non-PUS contexts, the classes
            provided by the OBS Framework are organized upon two layers of abstraction as
            illustrated in the figure:<Figure>PUSCompatibility_2</Figure> The general idea is that,
            at the highest level of abstraction, the framework provides classes that are not
            PUS-specific but which are PUS-compatible in the sense that they can be subclassed to
            become PUS-specific. Thus, application developers who do not have to be PUS-compliant
            can use the top-level classes as the base from which to derive their
            application-specific classes whereas developers who need to be PUS-compliant can use the
            PUS-specific versions of the same classes. As explained below, the OBS Framework
            provides default implementations of the PUS classes implementing the more common PUS services.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="PUS Telecommands">
        <p>PUS telecommand packets are imported into the application process by a concrete subclass
            of <cls>TelecommandLoader</cls>. The OBS Framework provides one default implementation
            of this class - class <cls>DC_BasicPUSTcLoader</cls> - that can decode a PUS telecommand
            packet. A PUS telecommand loader interprets the telecommand packet and uses the
            information it contains to create a component of type <cls>PUSTelecommand</cls>. In
            general, a subclass of this abstract class is provided to encapsulate each PUS
            telecommand-based service type or cluster of related service subtypes. The execution of
            the telecommand is entirely encapsulated in the telecommand component.</p>
        <p> Conceptually, the telecommand component instance is created dynamically by the
            telecommand loader after it has decoded the telecommand packet. In practice, in order to
            avoid dynamic memory allocation, the telecommand component instances are retrieved from
            a <a HREF="InstantiatorGeneratorMeta-Components.html#DynamicFactories">dynamic
            factory</a>. The dynamic factory for the PUS telecommands is generated automatically by
            a <a HREF="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html">generator meta-component</a> provided by the
            OBS Framework. It can therefore be exactly tailored to match the need of an application.</p>
        <p>In the OBS Framework, telecommands are intended to encapsulate <a
                HREF="DomainDictionaryEntries.html#PunctualAction">punctual actions</a>. In the PUS
            concept instead, telecommands may encapsulate actions that are executed over an interval
            of time. In order to solve this problem, the OBS Framework introduces <i>PUS Telecommand
            Manoeuvres</i>. These are <a
            HREF="DomainDictionaryEntries.html#Manoeuvre">manoeuvres</a> that are intended to model
            the non-punctual actions associated to a PUS telecommand. PUS telecommand manoeuvres are
            implemented as subclasses of class <cls>PUSTcManoeuvre</cls>. Telecommands that must
            execute an action that extends over time do so by launching a manoeuvre of type <cls>PUSTcManoeuvre</cls>.</p>
        <p>For testing purposes, the OBS Framework provides a test PUS telecommand (class
            <cls>DC_TestPUSTelecommand</cls>) that provides a dummy and partially configurable
            implementation of a PUS telecommand.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="PUS Telemetry Packets">
        <p>PUS telemetry packets are implemented as instances of class
            <cls>PUSTelemetryPacket</cls>. In general, a subclass of this abstract class is provided
            to encapsulate each PUS telemetry-based service type or cluster of related service
            subtypes. The telemetry packet component encapsulates all information required to
            collect and format the data that must be stored in the telemetry packet.</p>
        <p>Telemetry packets are forwarded to their destination through a concrete subclass of
            <cls>TelemetryStream</cls>. The OBS Framework provides two default implementations of
            this class: <cls>DC_BasicPUSTmStream</cls> and <cls>DC_PUSTmLogger</cls>. The first one
            can generate an image of the telemetry data that is formatted as a PUS telemetry packet.
            The second one can be used for testing purposes: it archives the telemetry packets it
            retrieves in a circular buffer and allows them to be retrieved for inspection.</p>
        <p>Conceptually, the telemetry packet components are created dynamically when the
            corresponding telemetry packet is required by the ground. In practice, in order to avoid
            dynamic memory allocation, the telemetry packet components are retrieved from a <a
                HREF="InstantiatorGeneratorMeta-Components.html#DynamicFactories">dynamic
            factory</a>. The dynamic factory for the PUS telemetry packets is generated
            automatically by a <a HREF="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html">generator meta-component</a>
            provided by the OBS Framework. It can therefore be exactly tailored to match the need of
            an application.</p>
        <p> For testing purposes, the OBS Framework provides a test PUS telemetry packet (class
            <cls>DC_DummyPUSTelemetryPacket</cls>) that provides a dummy and partially configurable
            implementation of a PUS telemetry packet.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="PUS Services Implementation">
        <p>The level of implementation of the PUS Services is currently expanding as more
            PUS-related components are being added to the OBS Framework. An overview of the degree
            of implementation for each PUS service is provided in <a
                HREF="PUSServicesImplementation.html">this page</a>.</p>
    </Section>
</Chapter>
