<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Chapter>
    <Title> Source Code </Title>
    <Author>
        <Name> A. Pasetti </Name>
        <Affiliation>
            <a HREF="http://www.pnp-software.com">P&amp;P Software</a>
        </Affiliation>
        <EMail> pasetti@pnp-software.com </EMail>
    </Author>
    <LastModified> 2003-12-05 </LastModified>
    <Introduction>
        <p>At the source code level, the OBS Framework consists of two types of items:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <i>C++ Classes</i> that implement the <a HREF="indexConcreteComponents.html"
                    target="_parent">concrete components</a> and the <a
                    HREF="indexAbstractInterfaces.html" target="_parent">abstract interfaces</a> of
                the framework.</li>
            <li>
                <i>XSLT Programs</i> that implement the <a HREF="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html"
                    target="_parent">generator meta-components</a> and the <a
                    HREF="indexTransformerMeta-Components.html" target="_parent">transformer
                meta-components</a> of the framework.</li>
        </ul>
    </Introduction>
    <Section Title="Cpp Code Organization">
        <p>The C++ code is organized as a single directory (<code>src/cpp/</code>) subdivided into a
            set of subdirectories that gather together groups of logically related classes. Each
            class is implemented in up to four files representing: the class declaration, the class
            implementation, the class inline implementation, and the class <code>#include</code>
            declarations. If the name of the class is &lt;className&gt;, then the
            declaration file is called: <code>&lt;className&gt;.h</code>, the implementation
            file is called <code>&lt;className&gt;.cpp</code>, the inline file is called:
            <code>&lt;className&gt;_inl.h</code>, and the include file is called: <code>&lt;className&gt;_inc.h</code>.</p>
        <p>Note that the <a href="indexQualificationApproach.html#TestSuite">test case classes</a>
            and the regression test to run them are integrated with the framework code and are
            stored in the <code>RegressionTest</code> subdirectory.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="Cpp Code Documentation">
        <p>At architectural design level, the C++ code is documented by <a
                href="indexModellingApproach.html#ClassModel">a UML model</a>. At detailed design level,
            the documentation of the C++ code is contained in the code itself in the form of
            comments that follow the JavaDoc conventions. The information in these comments is
            extracted from the code and formatted by the <a
                href="http://www.stack.nl/~dimitri/doxygen/">Doxygen facility</a>. The
            Doxygen-generated detailed description of the OBS Framework code can be entered by
            following <a href="doxygen/html/index.html">this link</a>.</p>
        <p>Doxygen can also generate XML, Latex and RTF versions of the code documentation. These
            are however not included in this web site. They can be generated by editing the <a
                href="doxygen/doxygenConfig.txt">Doxygen configuration file</a> and re-running Doxygen.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="XSL Code Organization">
        <p>The XSL code is organized in two directories:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <code>src/xsl</code> that contains the <a HREF="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html"
                    target="_parent">generator meta-components</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <code>src/AspectX</code> that contains the <a
                    HREF="indexTransformerMeta-Components.html" target="_parent">transformer meta-components</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <p>A generator meta-component is implemented in a small number of XSL files. If the name of
            the meta-component is &lt;meta&gt;, then the following XSL files may be provided:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <code>&lt;meta&gt;Header</code>: generate the header file of the generate
                class. This file is always present.</li>
            <li>
                <code>&lt;meta&gt;Body</code>: generate the body file of the generate class.
                This file is always present.</li>
            <li>
                <code>&lt;meta&gt;Include</code>: generate an include file that defines
                application-specific constants that are associated to the generated class. This file
                is only present if needed.</li>
            <li>
                <code>&lt;meta&gt;TestCaseHeader</code>: generate the header file of the
                test case associated to the generated class. This file is only present if a test
                case for is generated as well as a framework class.</li>
            <li>
                <code>&lt;meta&gt;TestCaseBody</code>: generate the body file of the test
                case associated to the generated class. This file is only present if a test case for
                is generated as well as a framework class.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>An Ant build file <a
            href="../scripts/runGeneratorMetaComponent.xml">runGeneratorMetaComponent</a> is
            provided to run the meta-components. This build file can also generate some sample
            components that are included in the code delivery of the OBS Framework as an
            illustration of the usage of the generator meta-components.</p>
    </Section>
    <Section Title="XSL Code Documentation">
        <p>There are no well-established ways of documenting XSL code. High-level views of the
            generator meta-components provided by the OBS Framework can be found here:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <a href="indexGeneratorMeta-Components.html" target="_parent">Generator meta-components</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="indexTransformerMeta-Components.html" target="_parent">Transformer meta-components</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </Section>
</Chapter>
