<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Chapter>
    <Title> Transformer Meta-Components </Title>
    <Author>
        <Name> A. Pasetti </Name>
        <Affiliation>
            <a HREF="http://www.pnp-software.com">P&amp;P Software</a>
        </Affiliation>
        <EMail> pasetti@pnp-software.com </EMail>
    </Author>
    <LastModified> 2003-12-05 </LastModified>
    <Introduction>
        <p>Transformer meta-components are one of the building blocks that are provided by the OBS
            Framework. They are introduced to automate the tailoring process whereby the assets
            provided by the framework are modified to match the needs of a target application (see
            the <a href="indexDevelopmentProcess.html" target="_parent">framework development
            process</a>). More specifically, transformer meta-components can automatically modify
            the source code of an existing component to endow it with some new application-specific
            property or behaviour.</p>
        <p>In the OBS Framework, tranformer meta-components are implemented as <i>aspect
            programs</i> (see <a href="AspectOrientedProgramming.html">here</a> for an introduction
            to aspect oriented programming) using the <a
                href="http://www.pnp-software.com/XWeaver" target="_parent">XWeaver</a> aspect
            language and aspect weaver. XWeaver is an extensible, customizable and minimally
            intrusive aspect weaver that is specifically aimed at qualifiable applications. The mode
            of operation of the generator meta-components is illustrated in the
            figure:<Figure>TransformerMetaComponents_1</Figure> The code modification process is
            driven by a set of specifications that are expressed in an XML document. These
            specifications describe a modification to be performed upon the code of some existing
            building blocks. The XWeaver aspect weaver takes these specifications and the existing
            building blocks as inputs and generates the modified building blocks as output.</p>
        <p>The development of the transformer meta-components for the OBS Framework is currently under
            way and will be described in a future release of the framework. </p>
    </Introduction>
</Chapter>
